boot camps boot camps boot camps boot
camps you probably heard of boot camps
by now um boot boot camps have been a
thing since 2013 and we'll talk about
what they are but this video there's
only really one message be very very
careful about signing up for a boot camp
any of any kind particularly if you're
going to be spending money if you have
someone you love or if you're
considering a boot camp I strongly
encourage you to watch this video to the
end I'm going to share several stories
uh about people who have been to boot
camps and UNS solic stories um uh about
them and why you might consider them um
and what what they involve and whether
they're the right thing for you um the
answer is almost always no that it's
going to be a bad idea and you're going
to lose money and everything to show for
it and um that's my opinion other people
probably have had experiences some of
you maybe had really great experiences
please put those in the comments below
or whatever and make sure that we hear
your story as well so we can add it to
the list it's usually better to get to
to do a project based learning approach
that you've set up for yourself that you
can then de use to demonstrate that you
know how to learn and teach and and
teach yourself and and and grow and then
you know demonstrate your commitment and
ability to stay on top of things than it
is to go pay the money get a piece of
paper and leave without actually being
able to show anything for it which has
been fundamentally my experience uh and
hearing about people who do boot who do
boot camps um capture the flag capture
the flag is not a boot camp okay so we
we'll talk talk about CTF uh that's a
great question we'll ask that a separate
time so let's talk about boot camps
really quickly I'm going to share some
stories right away um the first story I
have is is probably the most disturbing
um I was at a pub I was actually if you
know my IRL streams is my favorite Pub
it's the pub where I met you know Jack
and everything and um I was actually I
remember the day I was standing right
outside the pub this was when I ran
skill stack which was a brick and mortar
sort of mentoring school learning
community across the street which if you
want to see I regularly bike there um or
have bike there you can go see there
there's videos of that and while I was
outside I a guy the brother of another
guy who who actually was sad he passed
away because of a a degenerative disease
um and we were talking we're talking
about that and many things you know just
shooting the breeze and he actually
completed a boot camp and and I said oh
my gosh please let me know this is 2013
when boot camps were all the rage and he
said and and this is almost a direct
quote he said I'm trying to get it right
he said well I'm $99,000 lighter and I
still don't have a
job that was what he said and if you
knew about this guy's
situation which was already economically
very hard right he had had he had to
really scrape up that that money in
order to do that boot camp um and it
just it just ripped me up inside you
know I felt kind of bad for asking
um and you know I I wanted to help him I
said well you know you can come you can
come over and and just hang with me you
know I I used to do that all the time I
would give away like free time skill
stack for people that I took pity on
which is really a bad I'm a really
horrible B business person right because
I used to give everything away for free
oh I don't know kind of like these
videos um and and so yeah I had him I
had him come over and he he kept working
on different things and eventually he
did get a job and was able to start
doing things but um um but you know he
didn't have he didn't he I I for
whatever reason and I'm not going to say
what what what one it wasn't about me
bragging about being a nice person thank
you very much I was not why I said it
but um I just remember I just I just
remember being like totally just like my
heart being just like wrenched um and
around that same time by the way it's
important that you understand that I I
started skill stack um with retirement
money because nobody was teaching ing
the the base skills as as I saw them
that they were needed on the job and we
were having a we were having a really
hard time getting a hold of anybody uh
to hire them at at in 2013 in particular
um and there's other videos about that
and but then Al the same time you know
people were also not teaching the right
right thing I was there's these these
all this stuff going down in in
educational the AP Computer Science if
you could even find it was no good I was
like okay we need to start skill te so I
did I started skill SEC and said okay
I'm going to try very you know awkwardly
because I had never officially taught
anything um you know this stuff and it
just occurred to me that the best way to
learn it would be to actually use the
real tools and I was committed from the
very beginning to have Project based
learning that was based on real things
and I did a whole video about that so
make sure you watch that and um but a
lot of that came in as a backlash to the
boot camp thing now full disclosure I
was actually solicited by a university
locally to run their boot camp program
so so let me talk to you a little bit um
about the history of boot camps really
quickly so you can understand where
they're coming from and you know I I was
joking earlier in a in the first take of
this video about the the you know
capitalism meets education it's you know
that's a great thing right that's boot
camps right boot camps and and and look
I am I am making money from these
YouTube videos so to a certain degree I
am not clean either right not
necessarily doing them for that if you
say how much money you make from doing
these videos you'd know that but the
point that's why I have a real job um so
the the boot camp thing is exactly that
it's money meets education um in in kind
of an ugly way it's completely
unregulated um and this is this is the
part I'm where I'm going to get kind of
Chatty right because this does kind of
get into a conversational area that I
have a lot of opinions on so uh and
there's many many many others who've
talked about this Ted dinter Smith comes
to mind who's talked about um how
Enterprises and and and uh understand
education better than some of the formal
academic institutions and I don't want
to go down that entirely amazing fun
rabbit hole right now but it really is a
debate about on the on the one hand
you've got you you have to understand
this dynamic in order to understand
where boot camps came from and why
universities are adopting boot camps
today
uh which is really weird to say but it's
true so um on the one hand you have
accredited universities who have to
submit their curriculum uh upwards to a
year in advance to a particular
accrediation to an accreditation um
organization and that means that their
that their you know syllabus and
everything in their course has to be
approved in advance there is no way that
and that any institution on the planet
dedicated to learning can follow that
and keep up with what's required to
learn and that includes me the reason
that I do um these videos the way I do
in these little tiny pieces and I have
you know skills like that I owe out
there now is because at any moment I
might have to change how I how I teach
this or how I present it in fact I just
did um one specific example of that is
like introducing the use of V code
before before the terminal and I have
been able to adapt uh and and change and
I was always able to do that at skill
teack which drove certain people crazy
by the way we had I had a professor of
Education who who pulled their kid out
uh of skill stack because I was changing
the curriculum way too fast I was
changing it you know as fast as I wanted
to so that's the other side um the Boot
Camp or the Private Industry I guess is
Will is willing and able to change
things as fast as they want and they do
um they they can change things really
great and I I did another video that
recently talks about this and I don't
remember if I linked to the video I
think I did um if I didn't I'm sorry I'm
repeating myself you can skip over this
but um but then and then you know fast
forward to something like 2018 2019 and
organizations like Trinity uh came about
which provide boot camp type learning uh
to uh projects to the university so the
university can do their thing and that's
when you start to see that there's kind
of a there's kind of a middle ground
there and that's what becomes attractive
but but the truth of the matter is that
when number one when you get into a boot
camp you're like really intensely
focused and that has positive and
negative effects um if you're going to
yoga training like I did I did a month
and a half uh a month this 30 days of
yoga training really intensive yoga
training and I became you know certified
yoga instructor and all of that and it
was amazing it was amazing I got to have
that the camaraderie of all the people
there um I got to really get to know
them I got to eat drink and sleep you
know the the yoga and the poses uh
everything I did was dedicated to it and
I felt like I got a lot out of that and
and for something like yoga training I'm
quite certain that I would not have the
same experience had I been doing the
weekend thing right where we all drive
there for the weekend try to forget what
we did during the week and and and focus
on something when when you're talking
about something as immersive and
important as yoga which has multiple
facets to it then yes I think immersive
immersion
therapy if that's even a thing and
immersion uh imers
uh you know education mive education uh
and learning I think it's it's
phenomenal it's fantastic and I think
for that kind of thing I could see that
being true for so there's a there's
another thing there by the way I want to
draw a distinction um uh you walked in
on a yoga talk let's go so so we're
actually recording a video um uh about
the bad or the the the dangers of of
boot camps right now so just so you know
you're being recorded I should probably
put that in the chat um so so yoga art
you know uh writer Retreat um there's
something about a creative immersive
experience that is very good and and it
promotes learning and it promotes uh
creativity it promotes I think output
but I don't personally believe that that
is as effective when you're trying to
learn something for the first time and
it's an Tech it's a tech thing that's
just my take on it now to be fair there
are things like what used to be called
hacker bace I forget the name of it but
there is in New York um there's there I
forget the god I forget the name of it
used to be called hacker space but in
New York they have a a it's essentially
a writer's Retreat for programmers and
you have to already know how to program
and I think there's an important reason
that they make that distinction by the
way to be fair I really want to do this
if I was ever to get the resources I
would buy a plot of land and I would
regularly have Retreats really intensive
coding learning Retreats um and I might
I might be tempted to try the whole boot
camp idea but I'm more interested in the
the idea of of these these Retreats
these hacker Retreats or these these
coding Retreats where you already come
with a certain set of skills right
you've already learned it you could have
a beginner or a pro and you come
together and you you help each other and
so you get the sociability of it and you
get that Association and I think if
there's one positive benefit of a boot
camp that's it it's the chance to build
a professional Learning Network uh
starting with the group uh I mean I I
maintain relationships with those people
from the yoga than or I'm still I still
follow them on Instagram right those are
those initial relationships I think are
extremely valuable and when I think
about um people who have had regular
experience teaching web boot camps like
I'm going to say specifically learn with
Leon I think if there's anybody that you
would want to ask about what how well
and good a boot camp can be uh it would
be something like uh the boot camps that
learn with Leon has put on um has
successfully helped many many people get
get get jobs very quickly by using the
boot camp approach and I'm I I would bet
that that Leon would agree that that the
one of the primary attractions of the
boot camp is this idea of Community
Learning and support and the inertia
that comes from from all of the people
helping each other out um and and I've
experienced that but it wasn't necessar
for coding or or or this kind of thing
and and um uh to be fair I actually did
try to
replace um the first version of skill
stack online uh during after the co
thing I tried to do this I tried to
create this kind of community feel and
have a really intense session and
everybody was dedicated you know seven
to eight hours a day uh during the
summer during two months and it never
worked after the first two weeks
everybody was gone because they didn't
have the time they did there wasn't that
same
Dynamic um and it was just I don't know
we'd Happ to get to land somewhere um
but you know it this just did not it
just did not happen it just it it just
did not happen it as much as I try to
promote community in the Discord and in
twitch and everything um and have a good
time it just there's just something
magical about being in person so that is
a lot of personal experiences and story
and you hopefully you can pass forward
through this to say that there the
positive aspect of boot camps is the
sociability the the the connections you
make and the motivation you feel by
being together in a group but at the
same time that can also be a serious
negative I have seen people on the job
who have done nothing but they felt like
they did a lot because they all sat in a
room together and they were all you know
they felt like they were synergizing and
they were you know piggybacking off each
other's ideas and they were eating
Donuts so they were had a sugar and a
coffee High going on and they didn't do
anything but they felt really good about
it because they had so many people
around right how many people have gone
to like to like the oh we're going to go
have a pub you know thing and you know I
I talked about a manager who used to
have the the doughnut meeting on Friday
where they would just did us all in the
room and we would eat donuts and there
was no agenda and we knew there was no
agenda and there was nothing on the line
there was no target to achieve it was it
was completely ad hoc and fun and that
particular manager IAL uh leveraged that
Dynamic uh to produce some pretty
amazing new ideas uh about what should
be done and how to fix problems but it
wasn't it wasn't that they we had a goal
and we got all in the room together
because honestly most of the time if you
want to be productive you need to remove
distraction my wife
recently um has become known as somebody
who has a lot of people around uh and
she leaves her door open at work I'm G
to throw her under the bus a little bit
here um and and she is there's another
video about Focus we talk about that
entirely and that's what I'm saying um
this the statement here is that that
group dynamic can work against you
sometimes so just be careful um that
comes from a boot camp and so my wife
she so she had to get some stuff done
and so she closed the door and everybody
was worried they're all like is there
something wrong with Doris is Doris
angry and and to a certain degree they
might have been panicked you know
and and I'm I'm paraphrasing but uh but
you know she she mentioned that a lot of
people came up to her and like is
everything okay and then because she
shut her door um because you know that
that idea of like being available and
and is is a powerful thing but it can
also work against you so make sure you
don't lose your focus by that and you
don't feel like you're learning uh when
you're actually not you know you're
having a really good time but there's
really no moment during that that you
get to test whether you actually learn
something or not so okay so the the
biggest positive at boot camps is is the
social aspect of it and being together
um uh but there are so many negatives
and pretty much everything else is a
negative so the first negative is cost
it's extremely ex you can ask me the off
topic questions later while after this
video okay so the first one is cost
these things are ridiculously expensive
like $99,000 for an eight-week boot camp
okay um I mean this is insane if they
charged you that much money for a
university educ you'd be paying which
they are slowly creeping up to you'd be
paying an amazing amount they the second
thing is is that they're not proven
right um the third thing is they're
completely unregulated so and I mean
unregulated and my goodness you should
have seen all the news articles in 2013
there were news articles about oh boot
camps are reform revising reforming
education across the world every was all
how awesome they are and then there were
all of the all of the news articles
about how much they had failed everyone
I mean one of them I remember one
article was there was there's this this
couple in California who started a boot
camp and they had people sleeping on
their couch and the the the woman this
is this is my memory of the article I'm
not trying to be chauvinist here the
woman would bring out cookies and
constantly bringing food and everything
but they didn't learn anything and they
took all their money and then these
people left and they started complaining
to the Better Business Bureau and they
said uh we're not getting any skills
here but they took all my money and so
it was you know it became such a this is
such a California Silicon Valley sort of
thing by the way right it's like oh
we're you know we're we're disrupting
education and uh blah blah blah you know
come come learn coding on our couch you
know and and then they take their money
and run and it was happening a lot of
people were doing this it was completely
unregulated so you've got overly
regulated accreditation for a university
that can't keep up and through the
completely unregulated sleep on my couch
and I'll teach you the code where's your
money
uh people and someplace in the middle of
there is is probably something but the
best solution is just avoid it all um
and you know and not have to deal with
it um uh and then the other story I I I
think I already told the story but I'll
I'll just tell you quickly so I was
actually asked um I was as asked I was
asked by two different uh organizations
Tech Talent South actually asked me to
run their their educational curriculum
uh and I and they they told I asked them
Point BL I said can I publish the stuff
that I do as well can I have keep it and
they said no it will become our our
intellectual property and I was like
well I don't want to do it then so
where's the lesson in here um the the
lesson in here yeah the whole question
about gold diggers right um the lesson
here is that a lot of times when you go
to a boot camp I mean learn with Leon's
boot camp was really great because they
encourage you to make very unique uh
projects that you would take with you uh
even though you were sort of cookie
cutter in them from a template
um you didn't end up with the same
project that everybody else who went to
the boot camp had which which people can
as this is according to Leon they could
have re they could absolutely identify
in an interview oh you're another one of
these people who went through X and Y
project in boot camp you have the exact
same project as these other 10 people
who applied who obviously have that same
boot camp in fact boot camps became so
bad that that people started
recommending against putting boot caps
in your Raisor made because could
actually count against you I'm not
exagger ating I am not exaggerating
there was a time you can re go to the
research on this it's actually pretty
old at this point and probably if you
were search for around 2017 2018 it was
at that point the company started
officially saying to everyone publicly
we do not hire people from boot camps we
don't we don't hire them at all and um
that if you listed a boot camp it could
actually act against you it was around
that time that I ran into another guy
who worked for the department for a
local college and and so I going to get
trouble here um I kind of just started
like oh really and I saw I mean he was a
nice guy and and we were hanging out and
stuff and uh um we it started to become
clear that he didn't even have like
rudimentary skills um and I you know as
him say Well what you know what language
do they teachers like that and so this
guy had been hired by by a
university um
because of in part because of his boot
camp he'd been through but you know of
his own admission he didn't really know
how to code at all even though he goes
well they they sort of talked about this
and such I don't want to get too
detailed because you'll find out who it
is and and then and then he you know he
his own admission he was he had a he had
a job so he wasn't stressed because they
hired him anyway um probably because it
was University um who you know values a
piece of paper more than they probably
should and um um so yeah but but in the
conversation became clear to me anyway
that that he he was a great guy and he
had a lot of um desire to learn but this
boot camp that he had that they had sent
him to certainly did not do what was
needed and the last piece of this about
the boot camp thing that I want to talk
about is kind of comical okay so um i' I
mean I've been watching the boot camp
movement and boot camp thing for quite a
while since at least 2013
and I've noticed there's a there's a
term in Silicon Valley called pivot
right it's like if something's not
working it's like oh rather than admit
failure um you do something called pivot
and a pivot is kind of a fancy way of
saying uh well you know we're just we're
trying to be more successful than we
already were without admitting that the
thing you were just doing was an utter
disaster did I say that out loud I guess
I did okay anyway so it's like about the
term pivot oh yeah we pivoted we pivoted
to this or pivoted to that they say it
all the time anyway um probably some of
the the the biggest belly
laps in a shot and foa sense look it up
um came when all of these boot camps
which almost all of them nine out of 10
easily were web- based right um they
were you know you can learn web
development in8 weeks and you can get a
job for you know a crazy amount of money
and you'll go work in Sila Valley your
life will be awesome and that did work
for a couple people and I'm sure
somebody in the comments is going to say
hey I don't know about you but it worked
for me and that's fine my argument there
by the way is that you would have been
successful either way so with or without
the I'm going to come back to that point
um when I conclude But but so these boot
camps the the comical value of watching
these boot camps try to Pivot during the
during the data science during the data
science which is a term that actual data
Sciences hate most of them
um machine learning people well
specifically right um and oh you're in
Davidson nice um so we're talking we're
making a video right now okay so so so
yeah so we had um so so it was really
fun to watch these boot camps uh try to
Pivot from web development to data
science and tried to add in data science
and the thing is this is kind of sad
about that is if you know anything about
machine learning science you you don't
you don't just cram data science into an
8 8we video um no it's not jalap but now
it does because you made that comment
don't make comments like that while I'm
recording thank you um so the point of
it is uh I said at the beginning of the
video which you weren't here to see that
I was going to be wandering about and
the main point was at the beginning but
you missed that because you weren't here
uh okay so the point of this is that
boot camps I have primarily been
developing developed for web stuff and
not AI stuff and having them try to
become a data scientist uh boot camp has
been rather entertaining because they
absolutely suck at it um and they they
can't do it because they don't have the
skills and they're trying to bring
people in who can actually teach machine
learning and data science and they're
failing miserably about all of that so
the fun part thank you for the follow so
the takeaway of that is that is that
even when boot camps are successful or
have been in the past they primarily
been based on learning web skills um in
fact I I know of no boot camp whatsoever
that teaches you backend development
skills um uh you know they may do some
and almost all of them are not Project
based um there are some though and I
want to make sure you understand that
like learn with Leon's the one that he
was doing you do actually walk away with
that with a couple projects um that
could help you to get to get the job and
keep the job and be really good at it um
so that's it that's it the the video is
simply I know it's long it's like walks
around all over the place um but the
takeaway is that beware of boot camps um
make sure that you get somebody else
who's in the industry to look at the
boot camp before you write a check
promise me that one thing if you made it
to the end of the video promise me that
one thing okay
if you are considering a boot camp for
any reason run it by somebody who is
gainfully employed doing the thing you
want to do and if you don't know what
that thing is that you want to do you
should have done that already there's
other videos about that right before you
even start looking for places to learn
you need to know what you need to learn
and before you can do that you need to
know what you want to be go back and
watch the videos about figuring that
stuff out before you ever get to the
decision about becom joining a boot camp
boot camps are like exercise equipment
they appeal to people because they think
if they sign up they'll get healthy or
they'll get a job they don't ask the
important questions they don't make the
internal commitments that are necessary
upfront they haven't got the proper mind
frame and so what ends up happening is
they're out the money the equipment is
gone they end up selling it or moving it
or donating it and they still and and
but in the case of a boot camp they they
also don't have the skills and they
can't pay back the money so just be
really careful that's a long wented way
to stay about that so I I'll end the
video now and then I'm going to go punch
J bye